<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true demands of the rebells in Ireland. Declaring the causes of their taking up armes. Sent into England by Sir Phelom O-Neale, their generall: to the Honorable and High Court of Parliament. Vlster, February 1.0. [sic] 1641. Published for prventing [sic] false copies already extant, or that may be hereafter printed. Avowed by R.P. Gent.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E135_4</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873455</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873455</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156427</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90156)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156427)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 24:E135[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true demands of the rebells in Ireland. Declaring the causes of their taking up armes. Sent into England by Sir Phelom O-Neale, their generall: to the Honorable and High Court of Parliament. Vlster, February 1.0. [sic] 1641. Published for prventing [sic] false copies already extant, or that may be hereafter printed. Avowed by R.P. Gent.</title>
                  <author>O'Neill, Phelim, Sir, 1604?-1653, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>R. P., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Hammond,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641. [i.e. 1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Not in fact by O'Neill. One of a series of tracts intended to turn the public against the Irish rebels.</note>
                  <note>Variant has "February 10. 1641." in line thirteen of text.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156427:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE TRVE DEMANDS OF THE Rebells in Ireland.</head>
            <p>DECLARING <hi>The Cauſes of their taking up ARMES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sent into <hi>England</hi> by Sir <hi>Phelom O-Neale,</hi> their Generall:</p>
            <p>TO <hi>The Honorable and High Court of PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vlſter, February 10. 1641.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for prventing falſe Copies already extant, or that may be hereafter printed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Avowed by R. P.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Hammond<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156427:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156427:2"/>
            <head>THE Iriſh Rebells Vnreaſonable DEMANDS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am commanded by the Noble men, Knights and Gentry of our Army now reſident within the Provinces of <hi>Lemſter</hi> and <hi>Vlſter,</hi> to give your Lordſhip an account of 'the reaſons that have induced us to take Armes, that the ſame might bee preſented to the reſt of the Lords of the Councell of this Kingdome; by which meanes our deſires might be made knowne to the King and State aſſembled in Parliament in the Kingdome of England, hoping thereby to procure redreſſe of our manifold grievances and oppreſſions, where with wee have been for a long time to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether afflicted, and could never yet obtaine any remedy of the ſame, neither by our hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petitions, nor otherwiſe; wee never ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:156427:3"/>
beene deſirous to uſe violence to obtaine the ſame, untill now of late. This State aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled for the moſt part of Engliſh, and them of the Iriſh Nation, ioyned as members thereof with them, being altogether diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to our Religion, have endevoured what in them lay, to take from us our liberties and lawes formerly enacted by Parliament, with the conſent of ſeverall Princes and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in England; whereby wee have uſed and exerciſed our Religion according to the due rites, and holy and neceſſary ceremonies thereof, which ſerved as decent ornaments to ſet forth the honour and glory thereof, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſuppoſe God is honoured, and with it well pleaſed. Which to defend and preſerve, being now ready to fall to decay, and bee brought to deſtruction:</p>
            <p>We have been forced to betake our ſelves to our Armes, to defend our Religion and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: And if the ſame may bee againe reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and our Religion tolerated, we ſhall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly lay downe our Armes in ſuch manner as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We deſire the Lawes of Queene <hi>Mary</hi> concerning our Religion in the uſe and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thereof, may be againe renewed, and now againe by Act of Parliament, as well the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of England as this Kingdome, may be eſtabliſhed and confirmed to us and our poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:156427:3"/>
2. That the Lawes and Statutes made and enacted in the reigne of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>Iames,</hi> againſt us and our Religion, may be by the Parliament of both Kingdomes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed and annihilated, viz.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That all Statutes made and enacted in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdome againſt any in holy Orders of the Catholicke Religion, as Prieſts, Ieſuites, Monkes, Friers, Capuchins, and the like, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their execution or baniſhment, may be repealed, and an ordinance by Parliament of this Kingdome made, whereby they may have free liberty in any part of the Kings do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, to uſe and exerciſe their ſeverall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to educate, teach and inſtruct all ſuch as are deſcended of Catholicke Parents, or are inclinable and deſirous to bee of the Romane Religion, without incurring any puniſhment either corporall or in their eſtates, or by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, baniſhment, or the like.</p>
            <p n="2">I. That all Acts and Statutes againſt publike Recuſants, taking away their means and land may be repealed, and that they may freely and publikely profeſſe their Religion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch trouble and puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="3">II. That thoſe lawes made for the aboliſhment of Abbyes Pryories and Monaſteries, may b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:156427:4"/>
repealed, and an Act of libertie made by this State to all holy and devont men, that will build and up-reare the ſame againe, to doe it without any let or impediment, and that the Ancient demeanes and Revenews of right ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining and belonging to the ſame, may be againe to them reſtored to the mainteynance of thoſe orders of Holy men, for which they were firſt ordained and erected.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That wee may have free correſpondency by Embaſſages, or otherwiſe with his Holineſſe at <hi>Roome,</hi> touching any thing concerning our Religion, that wee may have at all times a Nuntio Reſident amongſt us to informe us of his Holineſſe pleaſure upon all occaſions tending to our ſoules good, and ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="5">V. That all Lawes and Ordinances hereafter enacted in this Kingdome, may be by ſelect Councells of Romane Catholikes for the Romiſh Religion. And only of Proteſtants for theirs, and ioyntly together in matters concerning the Civill and Politicke govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the State.</p>
            <p n="1">VI. That wee may no more bee ſubiect in this Kingdome to the Crowne of England, and the Lawes and Statutes of the Kingdome; but
<pb facs="tcp:156427:4"/>
altogether governed by this State, and may have placed over us ſuch a Governor, or Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy, as may bee well accepted of by us, that wee may willingly ſubmit our ſelves to his ſubiection and obedience.</p>
            <p>My Lord,<lb/>
Theſe are the particulars of our <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, which I am commanded to preſent to your Lordſhip, and which are deſired may be conſented unto, ratified and confirmed; which if reiected and refuſed, wee doe intend to the uttermoſt of our power, to the loſſe of lives and fortunes, to maintaine.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Vlſter <date>Febr. 10. 1641.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips to command, <hi>Phelom O Neale.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
